<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>langchain on Cdani&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>https://c-daniele.github.io/en/tags/langchain/</link>
    <description>Recent content in langchain on Cdani&#39;s Blog</description>
    <image>
      <title>Cdani&#39;s Blog</title>
      <url>https://c-daniele.github.io/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</url>
      <link>https://c-daniele.github.io/%3Clink%20or%20path%20of%20image%20for%20opengraph,%20twitter-cards%3E</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 17:45:02 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://c-daniele.github.io/en/tags/langchain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Langchain pt. 2 - Data Analysis through Agents</title>
      <link>https://c-daniele.github.io/en/posts/2023-08-13-langchain-agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 17:45:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://c-daniele.github.io/en/posts/2023-08-13-langchain-agents/</guid>
      <description>Intro In the previous article I gave a very brief overview of LangChain, describing its main concepts with some examples with unstructured data in pdf format.
Following the same approach, in this article we will give a brief introduction to Agents and proceed by trying to answer an ambitious question:
leveraging these new AI tools, can we carry out data analysis on our DB without any knowledge of SQL nor of the data model, simply starting from a text prompt in natural language?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LLM - Experimenting LangChain - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://c-daniele.github.io/en/posts/2023-07-24-langchain-helloworld-pdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jul 2023 17:45:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://c-daniele.github.io/en/posts/2023-07-24-langchain-helloworld-pdf/</guid>
      <description>Intro For those unfamiliar with it, LangChain is a framework for developing applications that make use of LLMs.
As the name suggests, LangChain is based on the concept of LLM Chain, which combines 3 elements:
Prompt Templates: they refer to a reproducible way to generate a prompt. Contains a text string (&amp;ldquo;the model&amp;rdquo;), which can accept a series of parameters from the end user and generates the definitive prompt which is passed as input to the model The language model (LLM): LangChain integrates with the most important providers (OpenAI, Cohere, Hugging Face, etc) Output Parsers: allow to extract structure data form from the answers returned by the linguistic model The framework has 2 very interesting features:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
